all right here we are starting we're
back to the code we've done uh our hello
friend program we've got it installed
we've organized oursel a little bit and
we start it's time to learn the rest of
the basic parts of go um we're going to
cram as much as we can into this hour
and see what we can cover so um we have
our our program hello friend and we know
how to install it with go install you
can see that on the screen now what if I
could make it so that I could rerun it
uh anytime the file changed so I'm going
to use something called ENT which is
only available on Unix or Linux um if
you're doing good programming on
anything else it won't work um so here's
how it works ENT bash we'll use bash you
could use shell or bash doesn't matter-
C it means the whole command and then
we're going to say um you know we're
going to clear the screen and then what
and then we're going to uh run the
program go install do SL
CMD um slow so that should install it
and then we want to run it uh and yeah
so we could just do go run here but
let's go ahead and just do that make
sure it installed properly and
everything and then done so this is the
command that's going to be run uh if you
know term of velocity we cover basic
shell scripting that's we have to go to
for that to understand it um and then
we're going to do uh in fact that could
just be bsh it doesn't really have to it
could just do sh here yep um and then uh
now this however is uh a zshell kshell
or bash thing we're going to say if the
file of one is is has changed so CMD
main.go that means if this whoops hello
main.go what this command does is it
says if that file changes in any way run
this program so uh which it doesn't like
is there no such thing as sh
doc well I didn't know that I guess it's
just
bash wait
what go command. install H
hello oh I put it done on there there's
no necessary for that I don't know why I
did that it was dumb all right there we
go so so now it's clearing the screen
and it's rerunning it just to prove it
it's running every time
um let's do this let's
say uh SL CMD hello main
oops come on
Rob uh.
go I don't know if you can see
everything on there the screen's a
little bit
weird let me put it down just a little
how's that that's better okay
so uh I mean it's kind of better
so uh we're doing chat right now we're
uh making a video about coding and go
so here's a program if we change it to
friend we can say hello Rob I guess I
should I say Doris let's do doors more
fun that way you see how the program
changes so I can actually reduce the
size of this a little bit I'm just doing
contr a and then JJJ down this is t-o
config that you can learn about into
terminal
velocity um so anyway so this is the
program right and but wouldn't it be
great if we could make this instead of
saying hello we could maybe make another
program called greet and then we would
give it the
name uh you know here so the command
would be greet space and then a thing so
we're going to get to there today I know
that seems like a s simple thing but I
want to go through it kind of slowly
meticulously so you can deconstruct
everything that's going on so the first
thing is to introduce variables which we
already talked about variables in a in a
programmatic sense F of um you know in
in an argument and parameter sense you
know uh 2x uh + 3 4 y - 2 or something
so these the X and the Y those are
variables in this case they're also
arguments and parameters um I mean
they're they're parameters and and we
talked about that already but I just
want to remind you about that so when we
what I want to show you here is that the
equals in this case uh does not mean
assignment uh it means is equal to or
this is this thing and in that sense it
is kind of a
definition um so you know and and we're
going to actually make one of these
later we'll we'll keep that up there
because we're going to make this later
let's put a to-do there uh you know
we'll make a we'll make an actual
function in a bit but for right now
let's just keep it as it is and so let's
say if we wanted that the word Doris to
be in a variable we could Define a
variable called and I'm going to change
this up don't worry so we want to have
the name equals uh Doris
right and notice there's no semicolons
or anything declare to not use this is a
warning from uh go bimo so you know in
Shell we would have done something like
this right well that's not a thing
that's not a thing and go at all um
there's there's a number of things we
could do here because it's print Ln
print Ln is special it automatically
adds a space and um and you know I can
and it will automatically interpret
whatever the type is so you know print
Ln is is kind of special but it doesn't
work I'm just telling you about it
because you can put a period here and
you see it's going to put a space there
right so again println is is special
because it it doesn't con detate them it
does each one and puts a space between
it which is useful for like basic output
but but not for what we want to do here
for this we want to use the concatenate
operator or the plus and so what that
would say is it's like I want this to be
added to the other string right and now
you see it says hello Doris and there's
no space so we have to add a space here
and it'll give us everything we need so
uh one last thing that you can also do
is you you already know this from the
last video but you can use print F
instead and you can use a placeholder
here and you could say percent s oops V
sorry s is is shell and then name now
that that says let's put this thing
wherever we want
to and you know do it that way um I
already showed you this but you can this
we're not going to go into this you can
actually read about it I just pushed
capital K and you can go read about
print app uh and other things like it um
there are is a a whole host of things
you can do to the V uh to to make it you
know different um so it's not line
returning for example let's put the line
return there or sorry the Line Feed
whatever you want to call it um if I put
uh you know we'll put 10 here uh and now
I change the name so I can say name
equals I want to show you the variable
is just a box so name equals
Rob and you'll see that it will it will
do both but you see how it SPAC them
kind of appropriately right um and that
is because of the tent now if you dash
uh it'll do the opposite of that um and
yeah it's it's like making sure there's
10 spaces before the period I don't know
why you would do that but you get the
point you can like um do formatting and
line up and all that chz um sometimes we
might want to put a color in here which
we're going to get to in a couple in a
couple um sessions but so this is print
up and so this has been an introduction
to variables uh how they can change and
um how they can hold different things
and particularly in this case a string
so we've only talked about a couple
basic types you know strings booleans
and and numbers we're going to break
down all the Primitive types today and
we're going to break down uh complex
types which are made up of other types
so we're going to do all of that within
the next hour um and trust me there
going to be a lot to cover so let's
let's keep going um the next the first
thing you need to know here is that uh
when it comes to variables there is the
scope so you can decide where the
variables live and if we want to make
another sub I'm using that fun that word
very specifically uh we want to put
another couple one maybe we want to
factor these things out right because it
seems like I could you know I'm changing
the variable and I'm recalling the same
thing so let's factor that out how do we
factor that out into another sub routine
uh and I'm I promise you I'm going to
Define sub routine and procedure for you
in just a second so let's do that let's
do Funk um
uh we'll call this uh I don't know greet
you could say say hello you could say
greet whatever and now we have a
function so a function is defined as
being you know having the keyword
function at the beginning in this case I
said it was a sub routine in a procedure
stay with me um and we're taking the
steps here the the main ones and we're
going to put it inside of here and it
kind of goes without saying right well
where where do we get the name variable
from right well now we have to pass an
argument so we're going to say name
we're going to put it here but we're
going to give it a type so now it's a
string this is the first time since
you've been with me that you've used a
type the name of a type so we're
actually saying this thing is of type
string so as I said before at the
parameter and and and thing X and Y in
this case these are you know if you're
doing algebra these types are always
numbers right or particular type of
number in this case whole numbers or non
whole number numbers we're going to get
there so right here we have the name
thing let's get rid of this we don't
need that you can actually pass that as
a variable by the way um and so if I
once you figure out how how much space
you need um so here we print and greet
and we have name here now if what
happens if I leave it off right let's
let's let's do that first so but the
point of this is is as soon as we get
that in there we don't need this anymore
and we can now do this instead we could
say
greet and we could say
Doris and we can pass the argument not
to be confused with the parameter into
the parameter variable uh and now we can
do that we can change this whole code is
to greet goris and greet Rob and now
we've got you know uh it's G starting to
yell at us why is it yelling at us
because we don't have name we didn't
open up a parameter variable SLO is
thing up here in the uh signature so
we're going to add one we're going to
say name and string and now that'll open
it up so that it allows it to be passed
in that strict typing of parameters is
one of the single biggest advantages of
go over other languages oh hey how you
doing Raiders great to see you all right
so we're just coding and go we're making
a video but I'm just going to keep on
talking I appreciate you being here B7
so we are doing uh just a quick little
thing for my Raiders uh you'll see the
little flashing red that means I'm
recording videos for YouTube thank you
for being here I really appreciate it
love you um and we are coding go from
the get-go uh coding from the GetGo it's
called and we are on the third video of
coding and go from absolute zero so
there's two other videos on YouTube you
can go check that out okay great um and
your bit your your chat is safe though
it's not on the screen so you're all
good um all right so here we go we've
got so we've got a function we broke
this function out and down here you can
see it running at the bottom of the
screen and um by doing that we simplify
it right and it's called I call it a sub
routine so let me let me talk about the
terminology here for a bit um and this
is actually written about in uh in here
so document all the things hi there
let's talk about that okay so what we
have what's called we have a function we
have a
procedure uh you know and we
have uh sub routine okay and a lot of
people are going to use these terms
differently uh I'm going to tell you how
I think they should be used um a sub
routine is uh any any
collection of
steps or instruction c
s uh
period uh within a block so it's usually
a block and what's a block uh what's a
block a block is anything within uh
curly brackets and and go H you guys
know the other languages you know that
that blocks are defined differently um
and and so so anything with curly
brackets um anything collection of St
that a procedure is um uh is a uh
specifically a
collection uh of
instructions uh in a block in a sub
routine
right in a sub
routine okay and a function is um let's
see a uh let's see internal
calculation or instructions with a
specific output return
value like math okay
so this is sometimes called a true
function
um you why do we have to say true
function because the keyword Funk or FN
depending on the language you're talking
about has been taken over it's been
taken over and it's become known to use
everything but in Pascal anybody old
enough to Pascal Pascal SQL there are
several languages where you have to use
a different keyword to define a
different collection of instructions a
sub routine a block whatever you want to
call it um and it's super important that
at this stage in your learning since
you've just learned a code that you
think differently about them because it
will make you a better coder from the
first day um a function is defined as
being something that has a very specific
return value um that in general has no
side effects Pascal we love it don't we
um and it has no side effects and by
side effects I mean it is affecting
things outside of its block you remember
the block is everything with en curly
bra brackets right so and there's
actually one other thing here that we're
talking about and that is called scope
it's like it's like how visible a thing
is to other things that's really all
scope is and it's the same in English so
um you know when a function a function
we were say in programming we say a
function has very limited scope that
means nothing happens outside of its
block and
everything any change to the system
that's going to happen is not going to
happen it's going to come as a return
value and then something called the
collar the collar is the thing that
called uh the other
thing it's called the collar how's that
for a for an
academic oh God I cracked myself up that
the caller is the call is the thing that
calls the other
thing I like having simple definitions
because they're just so much easier to
to I you know
anyway so sometimes usually the caller
is another sub routine procedure
function or something right um but it
caller has its own scope um but that's
important that you know that right so
you have the one thing it's kind of like
you have one program that that runs
another program that's the caller okay
so um and and the scope so the scope of
a function is uh you know all of the
things that are going to happen they
happen inside of the block and the only
thing you know about it is that it
returns something and the thing that
comes out of it like a machine or a
factory sort of thing is can then be
used by the caller and the caller can
decide what it wants to do with the
thing okay um and this is actually one
of the greatest advantages of learning
go as a first language is because
because the return types they're called
are strictly typed and this is actually
one of the reasons this is this kind of
a side note that I struggled so heavily
um to help you learn coding with a
language like bash or uh even python
because the return values are kind of
all over the board and stuff and and
you're going to see here what I mean by
that so a procedure a sub rotine is any
so both a function and a procedure are a
subotin in my world um but a
procedure uh is not a function a
procedure is a bunch of bunch of steps
you know like you would give the
military even or somebody um to do that
are going to affect their environment
they're going to you know go do this go
do this go do this now and everything
they do is going to affect their
environment um whereas a function is
more like a machine you put stuff in the
machine and the Machine does what it
says and then it comes out and it gives
you something out of it so thinking in
terms of a procedure versus a function
even though they both have a fun keyword
is is worth it to me um and I'll tell
you right now if you when even though
they both have a funk keyw if you keep
your functions separate from your
procedures in your code your life will
be easier uh because raise your hand
which one do you think is easier to test
we're going to write a unit test case
here we already did one we're going to
do another one what one is easier to
test pretty obvious right it's obviously
easier to test a function because a
function you always know
that you can just run the function give
it a set of parameters and arguments uh
into its parameters and then you can
look check for if it get the result is
the expected value that's super duper
duper easy to test
right let's say you want to test a
procedure that makes several changes to
the system creates a file it you know it
does all this other stuff and everything
how do you test
that right A lot of these a lot of these
procedures by the way it will return a
return value about whether it succeeded
or it failed and that would be shill was
it able to do all of the changes to the
system that you told it to do right and
if so great you get a success return
value and then you have to trust the
return value to mean that all of your
requested changes have been made it's
almost like giving commands to you know
a general or whatever you know and
you're saying okay go do this thing and
it's like okay all the things you asked
for have been successfully completed but
if I were going to validate that how do
I do
it I have to have something or someone
out there validating the criteria for
success for every single thing I'd have
to have you know the measurement of of
this effect over here and the
measurement of this effect over here and
this effect over here in order to test
the thing you have to have a
comprehensive system that is is able to
know about the entire system and so and
so it's much harder to test a procedure
than it is to test a function and this
is the this is the fundamental argument
between people who argue for procedural
programming versus functional
programming and at some point you get
drawn into one of these arguments and
now you know what the argument is about
uh and by the way both of them have
limitations obviously but but the
functional people would would turn
everything into a function that's got
one specific return value and you know
that can then they would combine a bunch
of functions to make to increase
complexity um and but but now you know
you know the the fundamental idea behind
that when when we talk about programming
paradigms which I should put another
word here for you um a paradigm is uh
how to look at the world right so a
programming Paradigm is like like how do
we approach programming what what do we
make it how do we make programming look
at the world as as as if everything was
was an object or everything was a
function or everything is an event you
know and so that's this is the language
I don't want to get too deep in the
woods on this but but now you at least
know what these things are so you can
you can talk about them so back to
variables all right so let's get back in
the code so we're now looking at the
code and while we're at it since we just
got got done talking about functions
let's go ahead and for the fun of it uh
uh this is actually a procedure uh okay
by the way can anybody think about how I
might be able to make this into a
function instead of a
procedure pause the video and test
yourself how could I let's make a
function first but I want you to start
thinking about this how can I make
this a function
it can be done all right so if what is
this up here it's right now it's kind of
a procedure right so let's make another
one let's make it say uh calculate slope
what is it
line um I let's just say
double let's say double double double X
okay but but what is X x is now a number
let's call it an INT so this is your
second type that you know about and we
can say okay it's going to turn it but
now this is this is different this is a
function that means it has a return
value I haven't seen one of these before
so here it goes the return value comes
right here and we're going to say what
type of thing is going to be returned
well it's going to be an INT we don't
know about the name if we wanted to if
we want to give the name a name you know
we want to give the return value a name
we can do that and go and sometimes it's
valuable to do that we'll get into that
more but most of the time it's not
necessary so we can just say int and
then it's giving me a problem you know
I'm just going to say return zero for
now and and because it's not done yet
right so so let's do that so let's say F
ofx = 2x all right so this is this is an
actual function the same as a pure
versus unpure functions yes that's what
I call them or true function that's the
people have had to say that because the
the name function has been commandeered
um I feel like that's one of the
greatest failures of computer science is
so many people using the word function
procedures and subroutines when it
really isn't a function at all and um
it's kind of sad so so I had to go into
this big spiel about it so you would
know the difference uh these days you'll
have people say true function or pure
function that's what they mean um and so
that's all we're going to talk about
that but here you see we have this is a
very very true function because we have
it returns one value right now currently
it's broken all right so let's actually
write some code to test this right away
you already know this we did it already
but let's um let's write um we already
did this let's go in our
Command I'm going to go D dig down here
um and we're going to we wrote a test
code already and we're going to write
main. test and so we have another thing
to test okay so
Punk uh and we're going to try this is
an example based test for now um and
we're going to say example
uh double all right so and by the way I
don't know if you noticed but the name
has to be the same as the function which
is a whole thing we'll get into later
what is the output going to be well I
don't know let's say that if I say if I
call Double Double two what should the
answer be four
right all right so by the way let's
change our test now so I'm going to
change our test
oopsie um I'm going to change our
test I just am not coding right well
today um we're going to change our test
and we're going to say rather than doing
all
that uh let's do this let's do ENT go
test go let's see go
test all right there's no test files
here right so what we want to do is we
can go test do do dot dot and that will
test everything okay all the way down in
your program so what we're going to do
is we're going to change our ENT program
uh to clear the screen and to do go test
and that will not only test this but any
test here or down and that is a go thing
that is not a shell thing so that's
going to instead of um so that's going
to run our test for us uh and you can
see we're failing a couple different
tests here okay uh at this point it's
it's getting kind of hard to see the
test on the same screen so what I'm
going to do is um like get rid of this
or break it out into its own screen
which I don't remember the command for
that um there is a command to break out
a uh a t-u window into its own pain into
its own window but I haven't done it in
a long time I'm going to ask my API um I
mean my chat how how do I break out a
t-mo pane into own window
I think it it's is it Z I think Z is
zoom but it doesn't break it out so I
want to break it out I want to break
that pain out into its own thing I don't
do this very much so I usually just
start with separate windows but I made a
pain because of the stream um
so uh okay so let's see
here control B yes I
know that will move the Active Pain to a
new window with the same
session it's says exclamation point will
move the Active Pain interesting okay
let's try
that um let's try that
so um I mean double quotes just splits
it that's not what I wanted so um
exclamation point yeah there we go
that's what I wanted okay so it was it
was exclamation point that's what my AI
said so so now we have these two things
and by the way these are both windows uh
I use Windows over these little things
across the top because I can never read
them one of the reasons I like this
better is it gives me my directory also
shows me the file that's open so this is
kind of cool because now I don't have to
close the file um I can do you know I
can do CMD which is you know my my my
neam likes it a lot better when I don't
close it all the time as you see it's
updating it this is a t-mo thing control
a uh W to see the windows okay so and
then I have my my test here uh I can
actually update this with comma and say
test so now I can see all my windows and
you know you might have your own way of
doing this but this is this is how I do
it um okay so we're running Main and
Main seems to be failing right because
we changed the output so let's go ahead
and fix that unit test because we
changed it without changing our unit
test that was bad of us so me so I'm
going to go ahead and make a new one and
I'm going to CMD uh hello mainor
test and I can now change this we know
we're not getting hello friend anymore
so we know what we're getting so I can
actually make the test pass I can
actually I do this all the time uh I can
just copy the output of the test and put
it into the test case and make it
succeed um you know which is horrible of
me to do
right so I just copied there's an easier
way to do that but I'm trying to save my
stuff for you okay so that did not up
dat Okay the reason that didn't update
is because our ENT is too limited um
what it's doing is it's only looking for
main main.go changing so we're actually
going to change this to be um uh a list
and we're going to say um I mean you can
do ls-1 you can do find there's a whole
bunch of things you can do here um I'm
going to do find anything
dot anything that has the name
Dogo okay if any of those files changes
I want to rerun okay so now it fixed it
so but the other one is failing so let's
make that one not
fail um by implementing it so we could
say two here we could put uh 9 9 is 18
put 18 here all right so there's a
little bit of our test code all right so
now let's go back and update uh the the
test code why isn't that one showing the
program it's testing that one should
have oh there we go okay uh and then
we're going to go back into the main
here so let's make it work so instead of
returning zero uh I don't really need to
do a variable here right I could I could
say uh you know something some and this
is the wus operator so this is exactly
the same so
VAR VAR uh VAR doubled if I want I'm not
doing this but if I did I could say VAR
doubled uh is an INT so we declare it
and then we say
doubled uh equals x uh x * 2 right and
then declared but not done now way
return
doubled okay I'm deliberately writing
this the way a beginner would write it
um because it doesn't always come to you
that you can simplify this so that's the
first iteration right so and you might
want to keep this in your in your notes
um you know I I'm actually going to keep
it in here uh just so you guys can see
it um because because I want you to see
that it's getting simplified so let's
actually rewrite this um so let's first
of all see if it's working so let's go
look at our
test we have to go back to the window to
test it but I can just toggle with AA in
my
case uh let's go to the tests where is
it uh here we go so wait am I running
the
test oh here we go
[Music]
so um wait what oh let's go test on this
one test all right
so there we go so that's we got there's
my dog um so we got we got to test this
test is still run running we're still
failing the test
um why are we failing the
test why are we failing the tests I
don't know let's try it
again X
double
um we should not be failing that
test why are we failing what am I
missing we're missing something obvious
I don't know what it
is oh we're not printing it we're just
returning it oh that's an important
thing so the the value is being returned
but it's being thrown away so we need to
take that value and we need to assign it
to something and print it right we could
say um we could say doubled equals right
this is normally you wouldn't do this
right but I want to show you so double
the it's like re wiress operator Okay so
doubled actually infers the type that's
coming out of the thing so it doesn't
need to be this is called a wus operator
and it says okay doubled and then we can
print doubled ft print Ln you guys
already know about this doubled all
right so that's going to get us our
four but what about the rest right so we
need the 18 well we can we can do the
same thing again this this is very
painful for me to do but I'm doing it on
purpose thank you uh because I want you
to see the pain so we're going to break
something here what's going to break
before I save this so anybody can you
think about what's going to break
here what's going to break
here I really want you to see this okay
it says you can't put another one here
why because we are using short hand let
me go back to the long hand here and if
you're a beginner knowing the long don't
do the long hand but know about it
because what we're actually doing it
when with the B operator is this we're
saying bar doubled is an INT and then
we're saying doubled equals but and then
down here we're doing the exact same
thing
again this this is this is what we when
we use the wus operator the way we did
this is what we uh ultimately this is
what we were doing and you see how
doubled is getting redeclared here it's
like you know so that doesn't make any
sense right so we could either do this
we could get rid of it here and have it
be declared in both places that will
pass the
test or or we can make one of them if we
if we want to get rid of this part then
we can do this we can put the wallrus
operator here and get rid of this
because doubled is defined as being a
function that gives us an INT right so
so the program can infer from that that
this thing should be an INT and that
happens Happ S A Lot in a lot of other
programming languages too that inference
about what the type is it saves you from
typing a bunch of stuff obviously but
that's what this operator does this
walrus operator it's an assignment
operator it takes the thing on the right
and puts it into the thing on the left
making a new one and declaring it at the
same time okay um that's a lot to put in
that little operator and some people
criticize go for being too magical in
that sense but it makes it you know
that's that Goldilocks thing it's just
enough to help us not have to write a
whole bunch of crazy stuff
um and then down here we have an equal
sign but if I do this again it's going
to fail because why because it's like no
you're trying to make a new one and you
already have one you can't reuse that
right if you want to use it just do this
and that uses it as a variable in other
words it's another you know it's a value
is coming out of it and it's going into
the other one and it's just replacing
the thing that was there in the previous
example and then it's printing it out
now this this passes the test but this
this is unnecessary and what I want to
show you is because it's so easy to just
pass these things we can get rid of the
variable all together and just call
Double two this a very functional way to
do things and we could say down here we
could just say double
n all right and now we have two very
simple programs uh there's even a
simpler way to do it later which I'll
show you but but that's you know that's
it's got some redundancy in it that we
can get rid of later with a loop but
I'll we're not there yet um so so that's
it so we've got it we that's a pure
function we have taken in some things
we've changed those things and then
we've given out another thing and then
we print it so I what I want you to
notice here is what is different between
Main and this and this gets back to the
earlier question I asked about how do
how can we make greet how can we change
greet from being a procedure to a
function
a testable function now it just so
happens this is one of the cases where
Go's amazing unit testability is kind of
hurting us in terms of learning because
what these example based tests do is
they use something called reflection to
look at the output and compare it to the
thing that's being tested and so it's
kind of magical and it's not completely
apparent what's going on but basically
main is being called the procedure main
it it says function it's not it never
has been it never will be the main
procedure which is called a function and
everybody will call it a function but
it's a procedure it says run these steps
and it doesn't even have a return value
so it is the definition of a procedure
sub rtin if you wish so it runs this
thing and you're looking at it you're
like okay well what's going on here I
have no idea and because the side effect
of running Main in this case is printing
stuff to standard output that is a sure
sign of you know a sub retainer
procedure it is affecting its
environment and in this case it's
environment is the standard output data
pipe it's putting it out there and it's
printing it now I know you guys think
I'm in the weeds here but I promise you
you'll be better coders by Annoying this
up front so so by by running main uh it
takes it and it it just it just it it
runs those steps and what are those
steps those steps are other procedure
calls that say Hey or sub calls whatever
you want to call them go do these other
things right but there's no return value
what's the difference down here nothing
happened until I captured the return
value and did something with it right so
double is a pure function it's a pure
function whereas main is a procedure
function and that means it's just a
bunch of steps but how can we fix this
well let's go ahead and test this let's
way if you ever want to yank an entire
function and go y a that says yank the
outer at function all of it including
the you can do if which is just the
lines inside if you AF it's the whole
function so I just grab the whole
function come down here and push p and I
can copy that whole function in one
command Okay so that's very valuable I
promise you for because it you know it
doesn't see line uh blank lines and
stuff like like like dap or Yap would do
so so here we have example Main and we
want to make it not main we want to make
it greet we want to test greet right all
right so we have greet here and right
away this is going to blow up right
because it's like no we don't have that
thing there's not enough arguments so
let's let's put uh an argument in here
let's say Doris give it a string
Doris and um let's try it again and of
course it doesn't blow up there but it's
not right right it's not doing both of
them and then I can have greet Doris or
I can have greet Rob so now um I can
test okay that's passing right do I
really need to test the main program
anymore really don't right because we
just need to test greet but um but there
is a better way to do this and I'm going
to leave the main test here for just a
second just to make a point so what if
we turned greet into a function instead
of a procedure what if we made greet
return a a modified string and this is
the very much the unix's way you know
pipelines at the end of the day are just
connected functions uh that are
operating on string data so so here we
have um greet with string and we have
this sync so rather than fmt printing it
what if we did this instead what if we
just returned it okay okay we got that
comma there so huh we were doing that
fancy replacement so you got to learn a
new function so here we go fmt now we
could you guys know I could just do the
I could just join it right probably more
efficient to do that let's do that
rather than to do let me show you
another way we could do it and keep it
exactly like it is we could do s printf
okay what does s printf s printf is
exactly the same as printf except for it
Returns the string instead of um send
instead of actually printing it to
standard output so and that let you know
that way nothing gets printed until we
actually print it but that is exactly
identical to the other thing that we
just did uh and I'm going to make a
little uh comment here because I want to
make sure that I cover Sprint up empd
Sprint up all right so um and so we
covered that but you know that is a
little bit of an expensive operation and
so let's just give it a string so let's
see we want
Hello and um we don't really care about
the line return right that's not in fact
you know so let's go ahead and give
hello name and let's join it together
with the plus can caate operator and now
we have this uh it says the string
literal is not terminated whoops yeah
there's an extra quote there all right
so and because that's so small we can
actually do this and we're good to go
now now in some languages in JavaScript
you can actually take this one step
further this is one of the reasons I
love JavaScript and JavaScript you can
actually get rid of the return value
because it's the last thing on the line
and in JavaScript you can also do this
you you can change the function
definition to be something like this
instead it gets really really fun you
could actually have it be um uh's see it
would be I got to spend a long time
since I done it but you can actually get
really functional about it so that it's
just you know that and that if you done
any python um it's like a single line
Lambda you could do that with a Lambda
function um but but once it becomes like
a function that's just doing one small
transformation and returning a new value
it starts to really feel functional and
and you'll notice this over time um I'm
spending a lot of time on these Paradigm
differences because you are going to run
into these things and now you'll be able
to speak about them but that's it's very
very very functional at that point now
obviously Maine is going to fail now
right why is main going to fail because
it's not doing what we told it to
there's it's not printing anything why
isn't it printing anything because we
told it that greet was no longer a
function greet is now a procedure I mean
sorry a function supposed to procedure
so we have to print it right and we can
do a bunch of things here right so this
is I mean it for right now we're going
to do it the Long Way based on what you
know uh but we're going to say print Ln
uh greet Doris and you know fmt print I
could have done that at the same time
but oh well and and we're going to run
that and we go back here and it prints
it out uh we forgot the periods but
other than that it looks fine so we need
to update
our um yeah looks like I killed the
period there right all right so wait
what
what what's going
on oh right because this I don't
wait why isn't it doing
it I should be
passing that should be passing people
why isn't it passing
that should be
passing oh wait it's example greet
that's
failing yeah it's a different thing
Maine was passing did you see that
example greet failing okay I I was
checking the wrong thing so so this one
is the one that's failing um oh right
because why because we're not we're not
printing anymore right but here's this
is where stuff gets kind of interesting
so I'm actually going to show you
another unit test right now and that's
using the testing library and um so
instead of having example greet we're
going to change this one to be testing
testing right and we're going to test
greet now when you do test greet now
that you know what an argument is we're
going to go ahead and pass it an
argument so the standard argument is
testing. T and we're going to send it a
t and this is you just have to know this
um you don't know what pointers are yet
but you'll learn it and so now we can
actually say that we want to do more of
a test on it um and uh you know this
doesn't fail unless we exclusively make
it fail and I honestly don't want to do
that with you right now I'm going to get
make it back to examples I regret my
decision immediately because I have to
tell you about pointers and you don't
know about them yet so let's do example
um
greet and let's actually do the print
right fmt
println I mean you already know this
because this is exactly what main does
so if main is passing you know this is
passing uh this is new so print n and
we'll go do this one and now our test
should be passing yep okay so there we
go that's the passing test all right so
let's regroup we we're burning up time
here we got about 15 minutes left um and
we've done a lot of things things we've
done a lot of things so please like slow
down and process this and see all the
differences here um but uh we're not
going to introduce pointers yet no God
no we're nowhere close to pointers we
haven't even talked about types yet so
um we're going to go ahead and talk
about um
so wait
what main. go Okay so
all right so we have our function here
we have the the old one that we did here
can you see let's take a moment to
regroup on the code can you see a way to
make this more like this function
here uh so right here we have this can
be radically simplified can anybody see
it should I jump right to the answer
here let's jump right to the answer here
we can we can make this entire thing
much much simpler called refactoring we
can return x *
2 and get rid of these
lines all right how's that something
that's kind of cool about functions is
when you put them next to each other uh
the formatter will automatically make
them line up which is really great um so
if you're writing you know if you're
writing operations uh functions like you
know things that double things and
multiply things I mean it probably goes
without saying that in math the plus
sign represents an operation and the two
things on both
sides uh plus two are operand a lot of
people don't know this um but I want to
make sure you know because you should
learn this you really should so what is
an operator okay an operator uh
performs uh some action on one or more
operands okay and an operand is the
thing in the in the idea of a plus is a
thing that's being receiving the action
uh receives uh the action of an operator
we're going to come back to these terms
a lot so uh it's important that you know
them uh again for no other reason than
being able to talk you know
intelligently with a computer science
person um that's what they are so when
we come back here
two uh is so f of x x is a parameter uh
you know we put the number in there
becomes an argument so the operand in
this case are X and two the operator is
the star okay and the star represents
multiplication so um there are a number
of other basic mathematical
operators uh in go and I'm going to
quickly introduce you to number of them
uh right now because we're covering
functions okay so uh and we're going to
write them really quickly but I'm pretty
sure you could figure out how to do this
on your own so if you want to pause the
video and write these on your own write
a function that that um divides by two
we'll call it half write a function that
um uh increases something by some amount
and write a function that decreases
something by some amount so let's let's
actually write them okay so I'll give
you the STS for these um and uh let's
see here so you could this is a most
place but you could write code to write
code
actually um so you want me to do
that all right let's do this let's say
uh
decrement uh
increment uh multiply
uh let's see
multiply
by say
multiply uh
divide divisor I guess uh what um these
all have actual things uhr decrement
multiply um we could do exponent
exponential right we could take we could
take the diviser of a thing uh there's
there's a bunch of them and I'm trying
to decide which one to show you because
there's so many cool ones um but I I
don't want to lose you so just just try
these okay uh I'm actually G to write
some code here so or I in um uh do
Echo uh
bunk uh
I let's say x
um let let's change and multiply
[Music]
have and they'll have divide to be
double uh because they want it to just
be on operators on a single operand um
so I mean there's a there a two there
but still it's implied and then um we
want to say return int so we have XB and
int and we have in
here and what else do we have
um wait wait I did that wrong in let me
say
return x times whatever right we're
going to change that though so
done uh does that look right F
function okay so I'm going to send this
whole thing to my
shell um I'm going to send it to
bash and actually generate the code for
that you could do that with a macro
other ways but we're just going to do it
that way so let change these decre
decrement we can say x equals all right
so return x
-1 uh we can say x +
one um now I'm going to show you a
better way to do this uh in half we
could say divided by two we can say
times two okay so these are the basic
operations in uh in go and there's a
number of other ones uh that we could
get into modulo and and everything um
but just so you know these are the
basics uh decrement and increment
actually have two other useful
Alternatives um that are just shorthand
and plus plus I'm sorry uh minus minus
and plus plus uh what that does is that
adds
one um is it does it need to be at the
end of the line I was afraid of this go
go does not like these see you can do
this other languages you can do this go
doesn't not like this um so it's not
going to let me do it I have to do it on
it has to be on its own line and that's
because in other languages you don't
know how what the options are like when
it happens like whether it happens
before or after so Dash Dash and minus
minus minus minus and plus plus are kind
of frowned upon unless they're on their
own line and go you can't even do it but
other languages will let you do that no
problem so I guess we'll just keep these
for now it's probably good so how do we
test all these you know how to write the
test code I am not going to write the
test code we are approaching the end of
this particular video uh I encourage you
to go write your own functions that can
that can you know do different things um
and you know write your own functions
don't have to return mathematical values
uh obviously they can return
Transformations on input they don't even
have to have input at all um you could
have them actually grab things from
their environment which is not modifying
their environment but inspecting their
environment to get something new and to
return it to you um and that's kind of a
gray area when it comes to functional
programming because like is that
functional or not I mean it looked at
it's a universe to see uh but it didn't
alter the environments at all but it
looked at it so does that count as
functional I don't know I'm I'm not a
computer science snur to that degree but
other people are you can go give them a
give them ask this has been a lot to
cover this has been an hour or so but
we've covered a lot let's
review so uh We've covered uh uh you
know what a f function is what a
subroutine is what blocks and Scopes are
uh we did cover an additional type we
learned about operators um we talked
about paradigms particularly the
functional Paradigm and I don't know if
you noticed but I spent a lot of time on
the functional Paradigm um and quite
frankly this probably should have gone
into you know another another thing so
right now it's saying we're saying hi
there um and we're using greet as a
function uh as opposed to procedure
but now we're actually ready to start
documenting things um we are going to do
one last thing before we do that I'm
going to put another one here and um uh
we'll probably put the uh I think we
should probably put the age calculator
here uh so this is this is uh this is um
uh something that um you know well I
don't know if we should do that
calculator Cal
calculator which is kind of stupid but
you know that's what we did we used the
calculator so let's actually the next in
the next session we're going to use all
those functions we just made and we're
going to we're going to make them the
brains of a command line calculator
which obviously already exists but um
it's good to see how that's going on and
what's going on and and and that'll help
us learn some other some other important
uh things out there um it'll also um get
us ready for later on we're going to
actually make um a our own domain
specific language where we do date
calculations between two points in time
and some really cool things that
actually have bearing with regards to
you know your real world work but are
also really fun when it comes to making
a text Adventure because you can also
calculate the real world time that it
has elapsed and decid of things are
happening so all of these functions and
procedures and stuff this is all going
to help us organize our code and and
move on to the to the next things that
we're doing um so one last look at the
code before we break today um so we've
got we've got again we've got the main
procedure you now know I'm going to keep
calling it procedure you might want to
not call it that around another go
person you you and I know we have a
secret okay we have a secret but if you
try if you use that word around another
go person it look like it look at you
like you have nine heads but now you
know what we're talking about okay you
know the inside secret um so here we
have a procedure for Main and we have uh
several functions we have three
mathematical four mathematical functions
and a string transformation function um
which is you know taking something in
it's changing it and then returning it
okay go ahead have fun with those and
we'll talk to you later